<?xml-stylesheet href="/rss.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Compliance is a Feature</title>
    <link>https://www.complianceisafeature.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Compliance is a Feature</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Erena Langley</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://www.complianceisafeature.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Not Yet For Our Robot Lawyers</title>
        <link>https://www.complianceisafeature.com/posts/not-yet-for-our-robot-lawyers/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://www.complianceisafeature.com/posts/not-yet-for-our-robot-lawyers/</guid>
        <description>Compliance is a Feature https://www.complianceisafeature.com/posts/not-yet-for-our-robot-lawyers/ -&lt;p&gt;The rise of AI tools is transforming the workforce - how will this effect day to day compliance and legal work?  It turns out that despite modern AI being able to write thousands of lines of computer code a minute, in its current form it&amp;rsquo;s unsuited for legal analysis and woe behold anyone who trusts it to do that.  What will it take for this to change, and when can we expect our own robot lawyers?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;if-it-can-code-can-it-think&#34;&gt;If It Can Code, Can It Think?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyone who&amp;rsquo;s been paying attention to the Internet knows that the new world of AI tools, spearheaded by OpenAI&amp;rsquo;s ChatGPT and now joined by Google&amp;rsquo;s Gemini, Facebook&amp;rsquo;s Llama, and Anpromothic&amp;rsquo;s Claude, has reached an unprecedented level of hype.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of the discussion has been driven by it&amp;rsquo;s incredible growth rate - while the rapid growing social network Facebook took just four and half years to reach a 100 million users, ChatGPT managed this in just two months.  But what&amp;rsquo;s got people even more excited is the incredible results we&amp;rsquo;re now seeing that has transformed these AI systems into something more mature than a simple chatbot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s what has led to recent statements like &amp;ldquo;AI will write all code for software engineers within a year&amp;rdquo; (Anthropic CEO Dario Amodei).  It turns out that, yes, AI is actually amazing at writing software code - or at least at &lt;em&gt;helping&lt;/em&gt; developers write code.  Which is astonishing, because software development is unquestionably a realm where deep thinking and building a complex mental model of the rules is required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If AI can do that, surely it can reason about other things too?  You&amp;rsquo;d think that the task of reading a legal question and working out what laws apply would be somewhat similar to computer programming - looking up data, getting the rules, and reasoning which of them to apply to get the rob done, right?  No&amp;hellip;not quite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-does-modern-ai-actually-work&#34;&gt;How Does Modern AI Actually Work?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem comes down to the specific ask we&amp;rsquo;re making of the AI - to not only reprocess the input it&amp;rsquo;s been given, but to actually make deductive reason about the law and the particular situation we&amp;rsquo;re trying to evaluate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it is, modern AI doesn&amp;rsquo;t actually reason at all - it&amp;rsquo;s just predicting the next statistically likely thing would appear in the text next as it &amp;ldquo;writes&amp;rdquo; a response.  Large Language Models - having analyzed huge chunks of the text on the web to determine what kind of thing should come next - are very good at these predictions and this gives the illusion of coherent thought, even though internally a LLM has no real concept of the logic of what it&amp;rsquo;s saying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This illusion is often good enough for a lot of what we consider as &amp;ldquo;thinking&amp;rdquo; that it doesn&amp;rsquo;t make a practical difference.  Of course, until it does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-problems-with-llms&#34;&gt;The Problems with LLMs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone who uses an LLM like ChatGPT will soon see a &amp;ldquo;hallucination&amp;rdquo; - a name reminiscent of the psychedelic 60s that is the actual technical term for when an AI makes up something that isn&amp;rsquo;t true just because it&amp;rsquo;s statistically likely based solely on everything it&amp;rsquo;s read on the web that something like that probably should exist.  These &amp;ldquo;mistakes&amp;rdquo; can be minor, or they can be as severe as &lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;citing precedent that doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist&lt;/a&gt;.   Though much AI research has been dedicated to stopping these hallucinations, it&amp;rsquo;s proved hard to do - after all making up output, which &lt;em&gt;usually&lt;/em&gt; turns out to be true, is basically all the AI does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also need to worry about the AI simply missing things.  Things are only significant to the AI if it&amp;rsquo;s seen large enough similar examples in the internet data it was trained on.  If something it&amp;rsquo;s been asked or something it&amp;rsquo;s read isn&amp;rsquo;t sufficiently able to influence the following output things can go badly wrong.  This can manifest itself in various ways, from &amp;ldquo;forgetting&amp;rdquo; about facts it&amp;rsquo;s already stated and contradicting itself to not &amp;ldquo;appreciating&amp;rdquo; how important a link between facts is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is all assuming of course that the LLM actually manages to see the case law in question.  LLMs have a limited &amp;ldquo;context window&amp;rdquo; - which is a fancy way of saying you can only pass in so much data to them as input.  Although with recent models these are much bigger than they used to be, there&amp;rsquo;s no way to pass in, say, the entire contents of WestLaw.  To get around this, modern AIs often use a &amp;ldquo;RAG&amp;rdquo; system to allow the LLM to request more input documents from some sort of &lt;em&gt;search engine&lt;/em&gt;.  The search engine typically uses a &amp;ldquo;vector search&amp;rdquo; to find documents that are similar to the LLMs on various axes request and return them to the LLM to examine.  For example, one axis might be &amp;ldquo;jurisdiction&amp;rdquo; where documents about countries starting with &amp;ldquo;A&amp;rdquo; are at one end and with countries starting with &amp;ldquo;Z&amp;rdquo; might be the other.  The problem with this, as you&amp;rsquo;ve probably guessed, is that all the documents are pre-ranked before the start of the query - there&amp;rsquo;s no live reasoning going on here, which means that any relevance not already encoded in the limited set of axes might mean the legislation is never returned to and never examined by the LLM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditional AI developed back in the 20th century was great at logical deduction (if A implies B, and B implies C, then A implies C, etc), but terrible at doing more freeform tasks like extracting information from freeform text or interpreting images.  This is why all our old science fiction series have ideas about unfeeling logical robots in them.  Modern AI is the other way around - it acts like it understands emotional nuance of a text, but can&amp;rsquo;t seemingly reason from the axioms contained within to, say, determine what the implications of a law would mean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-is-ai-good-for-computer-programming-then&#34;&gt;Why Is AI Good For Computer Programming Then?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given these problems, which sound like they could be showstoppers for coding - a domain that traditionally requires exactly this kind of structured reasoning about a large amount of input?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, let&amp;rsquo;s consider what LLM has to learn from when it comes to coding.  There&amp;rsquo;s an incredible &lt;em&gt;corpus&lt;/em&gt; of code out there that an LLM can be trained upon - over a billion repositories of code exist on GitHub alone - and all that code has a few standard forms and standard syntax that makes it particuarly easy to digest and encourage an LLM to produce something similar.  Put another way, the problem space is much smaller and the known available solutions are much larger than for legal analysis of law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact that code is structured is also a huge boon.  The existing &amp;ldquo;language server protocol&amp;rdquo; tools can analyze the code and, using the rules of the program determine exactly what other bits of code the LLM needs to look at.  Rather than having to construct a vector space analysis of all the existing code and libraries (and potentially miss relevant things) the AI tool knows exactly what else it should look at.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the biggest difference between coding and other use of AI  modern AI applications don&amp;rsquo;t just spit out an answer in response to a prompt and call it done.  When AI coding tools like &lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;Cursor&lt;/a&gt; produce code they make use of all the existing programs on the system to help check what it produces is okay. They use compiler software to compile the code they produce and check for errors (and if they find any they&amp;rsquo;ll feed the errors back into the LLM and use it to fix them without any user input!).  They use a linter to reformat the code to fix any layout issues.  They&amp;rsquo;ll even go as far as to execute the code and check the output does what it is supposed to, and if it doesn&amp;rsquo;t run it back through the LLM again to correct errors.  Along with automatically creating automated tests there&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of feedback and safety nets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This kind of thing just isn&amp;rsquo;t possible with a legal analysis yet.  There&amp;rsquo;s no existing &lt;em&gt;compiler&lt;/em&gt; for legal rules.  There&amp;rsquo;s nothing that can take a legal brief and check the arguments it makes make sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-future&#34;&gt;The Future&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is there any hope of AI tools in the future for law?  Yes, no&amp;hellip;maybe?  Right now AI &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; useful, but has to be handled with extreme caution rather than treated as a magic bullet.  Just like AI assistants for coding can help speed up a programmer, the legal AI tooling we have right now already can help a competent user tremendously, performing tasks like &lt;em&gt;helping&lt;/em&gt; comb through discovery, &lt;em&gt;helping&lt;/em&gt; check citations and look for reference cases, and &lt;em&gt;helping&lt;/em&gt; with a lot of the other basic &amp;ldquo;grunt&amp;rdquo; work of processing lots of text.  The key word there is &lt;em&gt;helping&lt;/em&gt; - not &lt;em&gt;replacing&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the future some of the existing problems can be addressed.  There&amp;rsquo;s plenty of research underway on how we &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; get AI to automatically check what it&amp;rsquo;s created.  While there&amp;rsquo;s no equivalent to a compiler or automated test suite for freeform writing or legal analysis, people are developing tools where the output from the original AI is immediately fed into a separate AI to evaluate, allowing the original AI to receive feedback and correct mistakes.  The jury&amp;rsquo;s still out if this kind of tight feedback loop will ultimately result in something workable or will just turn out to be a case of the blind leading the blind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, while there&amp;rsquo;s a currently larger corpus of code that models can be trained on than is easily available for legal analysis, this is something that can be overcome with effort and dedication by model developers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately the problem will most likely come down to a question of trust.  No competent programmer would currently trust a language model to produce code that can immediately be deployed into a production environment without checking it over first.  And this is likely to be the case for a long time to come - most respected programmers in firms don&amp;rsquo;t even deploy code that they&amp;rsquo;ve written &lt;em&gt;themselves&lt;/em&gt; without first writing some more code to check it does the right thing &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; getting a coworker to read through everything they&amp;rsquo;ve changed and sign off that it looks good to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it&amp;rsquo;s unlikely that in a parallel situation no matter how much AI tools improve someone competent would feel content using the legal analysis that came out of a large language model - swearing an affidavit that it&amp;rsquo;s true - without having someone competent review it first.  And this is much harder for legal analysis than it is for a simple code change.  Since someone has to not only confirm what was produced is good but also has to identify if there&amp;rsquo;s something missing - something like a particular clause of a statue, a previous ruling, or a regulatory advisory that hasn&amp;rsquo;t been considered relevant - that reviewer is going to at least do the legal work to understand all the background law and nuances of the issue.  And there&amp;rsquo;s the rub - that work is pretty much the same work (minus a little typing) as doing the legal analysis in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In the end only time will tell if AI tooling can ultimately significantly reduce the need for human legal analysis.  But for now, it looks like we might be stuck with humans for a little longer.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;- https://www.complianceisafeature.com/posts/not-yet-for-our-robot-lawyers/ - Erena Langley</description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Why Bitcoin Isn&#39;t Money...Yet</title>
        <link>https://www.complianceisafeature.com/posts/why-bitcoin-isnt-money-yet/</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://www.complianceisafeature.com/posts/why-bitcoin-isnt-money-yet/</guid>
        <description>Compliance is a Feature https://www.complianceisafeature.com/posts/why-bitcoin-isnt-money-yet/ -&lt;p&gt;Bitcoin and cryptocurrencies have weathered the hype to become surprisingly durable analogues to real world currencies.  But the ultimate goal of replacing the financial systems we have in place will remain elusive till they can emulate one critical aspect of modern monetary systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the lauded advantage of cryptocurrencies is that you can&amp;rsquo;t - other than by mining - create new coins.  This means that, thanks to the blockchain, bad actors can&amp;rsquo;t just conjure money out of thin air.  But ironically, the ability to do exactly this is how banks work that operate with traditional fiat currencies (i.e. non-cryptocurrencies like the dollar or pound).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-banks-operate&#34;&gt;How Banks Operate&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The commonly held idea that people deposit money into banks and then banks lend that same money back out to people isn&amp;rsquo;t really accurate with modern banks.  A closer analogy is that banks make a &amp;ldquo;promise&amp;rdquo; to pay out the &amp;ldquo;money&amp;rdquo; they loan out.  When a bank makes a loan, those loans are considered &amp;ldquo;assets&amp;rdquo; - because everyone agrees whomever they&amp;rsquo;ve loaned the money too will pay it back with interest, eventually netting the bank more than it had to outlay in the promise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what happens if whoever the loan was offered to simply doesn&amp;rsquo;t pay it back?  Then the loan has to be written off (as something that will never be repaid) and the bank will be devalued by what was outstanding from the loan.  Though since a trustworthy bank makes loans only to people that it considers will pay the loan back, the bank will hopefully be profitable as long as it writes off less money than it gains from interest on the loans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And what if a bank makes too many wrong calls on who will or will not pay the money back?  This is why Professor Jim Scott, who was the Director of Boston University School of Law&amp;rsquo;s Banking and Financial Law program when I took my LLM, used to say that &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; most important thing in banking law is &lt;em&gt;Capitalization&lt;/em&gt;.  As long as a bank has sufficient capitalization (money from the initial investors, good loans on the books, etc) it can easily weather a certain number of loans being written off before the bank will &amp;ldquo;fail&amp;rdquo; (like Silicon Valley Bank famously did in 2023).  Even a bank with some losses can be considered &amp;ldquo;trustworthy&amp;rdquo; as long as the regulations on capitalization are followed because it will be able to &amp;ldquo;weather the storm&amp;rdquo; of bad calls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because banks are considered trustworthy the financial system is designed to act as if the electronic promises banks are making during loans really are equivalent to money.  Through the magic of the ACH system and other such agreements whenever a bank makes a loan to a person that person can then immediately transfer that &amp;ldquo;money&amp;rdquo; to another bank and that bank will treat it exactly the same as if someone had walked in off the street and deposited cash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To all intents and purposes the bank making the loan has just &amp;ldquo;created&amp;rdquo; money backed by the assets it holds.  This financial process is key to growth in our economy and is what fuels investment that is the lifeblood of modern business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;in-contrast-how-cryptocurrencies-operate&#34;&gt;In Contrast, How Cryptocurrencies Operate&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, at it&amp;rsquo;s most basic, cryptocurrencies can&amp;rsquo;t be used this way.  Pure cryptocurrency banks, who are limited to making transactions on the blockchains involved, are only able to loan out up to the exact amount of coin that was deposited and invested in them because they have no way to &amp;ldquo;create&amp;rdquo; the coin that represents their additional assets (i.e. the expected eventual return on the loans they&amp;rsquo;ve already loaned out).  They&amp;rsquo;re severely hampered in a way that traditional banks - who can often loan out multiple times their funding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, of course, cryptocurrency banks could - if they wished - operate with cryptocurrencies much like traditional banks do with fiat currencies.  They could establish a system whereby the transfer of &amp;ldquo;promise to pay Etherium&amp;rdquo; from a loan could be treated between trusted banking partners as equivalent in value to an actual Etherium transfer on the blockchain itself.  While customers could then withdraw limited Etherium in the same way that traditional bank&amp;rsquo;s customers could withdraw limited banknotes back out of a bank, the majority of the &amp;ldquo;money&amp;rdquo; would exist just as agreements between the cryptocurrency banks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this would mean that cryptocurrency banks, in order to be trustworthy, would have to not only be capitalized by a certain amount of actual cryptocurrency but also regulated in the same way trusted banks are to prevent financial distress.   At the very least, they would need to establish a network of trust between cryptocurrency banks about who was trusted for making good loans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this&amp;hellip;this defeats the whole allure of a supposed decentralized currency.  You suddenly have to have a whole infrastructure - unlike normal blockchain transactions - that cares about who is backing the money.  Where most transactions are happening &amp;ldquo;off the chain&amp;rdquo; where they can&amp;rsquo;t be tracked (or, at least off the main chain).  And you&amp;rsquo;ve gone a great length to essentially end up with the same issues of centralized infrastructure and power that the blockchain was trying to avoid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is there some solution to this problem?  Yes and no&amp;hellip;as always it&amp;rsquo;s complicated.  Modern blockchain transactions aren&amp;rsquo;t as limited by ownership of coins.  They have the concept of smart contracts that offer the possibility of enforcing contracts about money that could be used to ensure things like capitalization, repayment of interest, et cetera.  This technology is being used to support DeFI (decentralized finance).  This allows much more direct entity to entity lending that is more fitting to the decentralized ideals of the blockchain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the vast majority of the &amp;ldquo;money&amp;rdquo; in the world is still represented by the trust relationships between traditional banks.  This is a fundamental problem that cryptocurrencies must overcome if they want to supplant the existing finical networks: How do they effectively capture this existing wealth generated by traditional banks &amp;ldquo;creating&amp;rdquo; money through loans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As time moves on I suspect we&amp;rsquo;ll see more hybrid solutions to problems with a mix of the old world of banking and the new world of the blockchain working in conjunction.  What that will look like however&amp;hellip;only time (and the market) will tell what we trust.&lt;/p&gt;- https://www.complianceisafeature.com/posts/why-bitcoin-isnt-money-yet/ - Erena Langley</description>
        </item>
    
    
    
        <item>
        <title>Simple is Difficult</title>
        <link>https://www.complianceisafeature.com/posts/simple-is-difficult/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://www.complianceisafeature.com/posts/simple-is-difficult/</guid>
        <description>Compliance is a Feature https://www.complianceisafeature.com/posts/simple-is-difficult/ -&lt;p&gt;Making things simple can be surprisingly difficult.  However, when after days of work what you have to show is one easy to follow diagram or a concise paragraph that can explain everything, that&amp;rsquo;s the sign you&amp;rsquo;re on the right track.  By making things simple you&amp;rsquo;re not proving what you&amp;rsquo;re working on wasn&amp;rsquo;t that complicated in the first place, but rather your skill and effort has been spent empowering anyone - including the busy c-suite executive - to be able to comprehend the issue properly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;compliance-is-complicated&#34;&gt;Compliance is Complicated&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compliance can be a complex beast.  It involves understanding a whole host of laws, rules, resolutions, and guidelines and understanding everything about how your industry works (the processes, the staff, the product, the customers, and so on)&amp;hellip;and then figuring out how all the former applies to all the latter, and what systematic steps you need to take to ensure you&amp;rsquo;re complying.  And finally, explaining that to someone else in a way that they can comprehend what&amp;rsquo;s important and what&amp;rsquo;s not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things I&amp;rsquo;ve seen when mentoring people in my teams is that more junior staff members often feel that they need to &lt;em&gt;express&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;share&lt;/em&gt; this complexity.  There&amp;rsquo;s many reasons for this, from wanting to show how much work they&amp;rsquo;re doing, to a desire to make sure that everything someone might need to know is available.  However, when organizations scale - when they grow and increase the number of staff - they have to be aware of the cost of having everyone know the details on everything.  Pretty soon employees find that they&amp;rsquo;re spending most of their time communicating, passing information on and around, with less time to concentrate on their own work.  We need to spend effort simplifying so these concepts can be expressed quickly and easily without much overhead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-cost-of-details&#34;&gt;The Cost of Details&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can think about the amount of information you share as having a cost. Not just the immediate time you and who you share the information with directly spend working on it, but also the time the people they communicate about this with spend, and so on.  The more succinct and coherent you can make an explanation the lower the cost - multiplied by everyone you hope will want to hear it.  Sooner or later busy people - people like the CEO and senior management who you want to have at least a cursory understanding of what your compliance team is up to - will start to simply drop things on the floor that they don&amp;rsquo;t have the time to spend on.  This means you can think of time your team spend on simplification as &amp;ldquo;prepping this for the C-suite&amp;rdquo; if you want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A surprising thing is that the person you might be communicating most to is&amp;hellip;yourself;  Yourself six months from now when you&amp;rsquo;ve come back to something that you haven&amp;rsquo;t paid attention to for half a year where you&amp;rsquo;ll need to get back up to speed really quickly.  If you can make it simple for future you to understand, all the better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;simplify-not-hide&#34;&gt;Simplify, Not Hide&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key thing to understand here is that we&amp;rsquo;re trying to simplify things, not hide things - we don&amp;rsquo;t want to create silos in the organization.  We don&amp;rsquo;t want to remove necessary detail but structure the way we communicate what needs to happen and why so it&amp;rsquo;s possible for someone else to follow the logic behind what we&amp;rsquo;re planning without having to delve deep into irrelevant chaff along the way.  For example, a flow diagram showing which rules applies to us can omit irrelevant paths and will be much easier to understand than the original source text of the rules.  A bullet list up front of the key points with links to the details will be much clearer than several pages of text that you must consume before getting to the nub of the issue.  Ideally you&amp;rsquo;d be able to express the heart of the problem in a sentence or two - your elevator pitch for why the work is happening - and provide follow up detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this is a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of work.  Not only do we have to decide what is and isn&amp;rsquo;t important, but also what is &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; important so we can express this first - and also ensure at the same time what we&amp;rsquo;re explaining can be expressed in a consistent followable narrative that someone else can digest easily.  While we now have automated tools that can summarize text, what we&amp;rsquo;re talking about here is going beyond that - creating a whole conceptual model and framework for describing the issue so we can express it simply and succinctly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What our goal is is &lt;em&gt;encapsulation&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;progressive enhancement&lt;/em&gt;.  We want it to be possible for someone to &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; have to learn every detail about the compliance issue to quickly understand the core ideas (encapsulation), and if necessary be able to get dive in and read more detail on particular aspects by consuming supplemental parts as needed (progressive enhancement).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we do this right, we can save everyone a lot of time - including any auditors in audits we may have to do, since now we can quickly explain to them what we&amp;rsquo;re doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;unexpected-complexity&#34;&gt;Unexpected Complexity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Complexity can come from many sources beyond just the large numbers of rules the company needs to follow and the bredth of the company&amp;rsquo;s operation, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Temporal complexity&lt;/strong&gt;, as things or opinions change over time.  For example, rules and regulations change as they&amp;rsquo;re modified, or your company may get a new legal opinion that drastically changes what you believe is and isn&amp;rsquo;t okay now.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Differing understandings&lt;/strong&gt; within the company about something in the company.  In my experience it&amp;rsquo;s not uncommon for one person to think a process or software works one way, and another in the firm to come across later and say it works another.  I can&amp;rsquo;t count the number of times I&amp;rsquo;ve sat down with different parties with diagrams I&amp;rsquo;ve created based on what previous employees have told me to only have to refine it based on &amp;ldquo;yes, well, but actually&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;.  Getting everyone on the same page can take considerable effort!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Large Data&lt;/strong&gt; that takes you time to go through;  You might have a large number of customers and be unsure if any of them are subject to a law or regulation.  The complexity here comes not only from the sheer number of things (which may require much automated processing since it&amp;rsquo;s too much to do by hand) but also defining process that demonstrates you&amp;rsquo;ve provably processed all of the data and nothing has been missed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this complexity is ripe for encapsulation so not everybody has to deal with the nitty gritty, but you&amp;rsquo;ll have to remain cognisent of the audience;  If someone is used to operating under previous versions of the regulation you&amp;rsquo;ll have to ensure they understand about the update or confusion will rule.  If different people operate on different assumptions about processes in the business you&amp;rsquo;re going to have to explain things to get them singing from the same song sheet.  As always it&amp;rsquo;s a balancing act.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;practical-steps&#34;&gt;Practical Steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we&amp;rsquo;ve got a clear understanding of &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; we need to spend effort making things simple to explain, let&amp;rsquo;s talk &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; we go about it.  Truth be told, this is a practice that we learn and refine over our whole careers, but I do have short list of advice I give to people I&amp;rsquo;m mentoring who want a quick leg up to better practice:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To fully be able to explain something succinctly is to understand it completely.  Don&amp;rsquo;t expect to be able to produce the perfect summary straight away, but instead work on scrappy versions of diagrams and bullet points as you go.  You can refine these as you learn more, but be prepared once you&amp;rsquo;ve learnt more to completely throw these away (or make them available as supplementary material) and draw/write something short and new now you&amp;rsquo;ve got better understanding to communicate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The military like to &amp;ldquo;BLUF&amp;rdquo; their documents, including the Bottom Line Up Front.  The internet calls this &amp;ldquo;tl;dr&amp;rdquo; (too long; didn&amp;rsquo;t read).  Either way, I like to put a summary of whatever I&amp;rsquo;m writing (email, word document, confluence page, even long form slack messages) at the very top.  And put it in bold.  And assume that it&amp;rsquo;s the only thing someone is going to read.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Similarly, if I&amp;rsquo;m preparing a &amp;ldquo;reading&amp;rdquo; slide deck (something designed to be emailed over rather than presented) then I like to have just a few slides at the start that I actually expect the audience to read, and then a clearly delimitated section at the end (an &amp;ldquo;appendix&amp;rdquo;) that contains all the details for the people that need them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speaking of putting things in bold, I like to abuse bold for emphasizing key points and action items in messages.  Just because I find compliance one of the most facinating things in the world doesn&amp;rsquo;t make this true for everybody!  Let&amp;rsquo;s make it easy for them to see why they should care about this email.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Communications work best with context but with limited waffle.  Getting the balance right in the company wide email can be quite hard - but can be greatly improved by taking just a half a sentence to say &amp;ldquo;As part of our effort to reticulate splines to get the flux capactiating we need to&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; and then providing links to documentation at the end of the email assuming that the email will be read by a new employee on day one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion-simplifying-is-how-we-think&#34;&gt;Conclusion: Simplifying is How We Think&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, we need to make clear strategic decisions about compliance work in the business if we&amp;rsquo;re going to have any meaningful impact.  Doing this is impossible if we can&amp;rsquo;t determine what&amp;rsquo;s important rather than just being overloaded by details.  We need to put the effort into simplifying the problem first till we have a proper understanding of the core of issue, and this way we can see the likely strategic outcomes of our work.&lt;/p&gt;- https://www.complianceisafeature.com/posts/simple-is-difficult/ - Erena Langley</description>
        </item>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
    
  </channel>
</rss> 