<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Compliance is a Feature</title>
    <link>https://www.complianceisafeauture.com/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Compliance is a Feature</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Erena Langley</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://www.complianceisafeauture.com/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Not Yet For Our Robot Lawyers</title>
      <link>https://www.complianceisafeauture.com/posts/not-yet-for-our-robot-lawyers/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.complianceisafeauture.com/posts/not-yet-for-our-robot-lawyers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The rise of AI tools is transforming the workforce - how will this effect day to day compliance and legal work?  It turns out that despite modern AI being able to write thousands of lines of computer code a minute, in its current form it&amp;rsquo;s unsuited for legal analysis and woe behold anyone who trusts it to do that.  What will it take for this to change, and when can we expect our own robot lawyers?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why Bitcoin Isn&#39;t Money...Yet</title>
      <link>https://www.complianceisafeauture.com/posts/why-bitcoin-isnt-money-yet/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.complianceisafeauture.com/posts/why-bitcoin-isnt-money-yet/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Bitcoin and cryptocurrencies have weathered the hype to become surprisingly durable analogues to real world currencies.  But the ultimate goal of replacing the financial systems we have in place will remain elusive till they can emulate one critical aspect of modern monetary systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simple is Difficult</title>
      <link>https://www.complianceisafeauture.com/posts/simple-is-difficult/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.complianceisafeauture.com/posts/simple-is-difficult/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Making things simple can be surprisingly difficult.  However, when after days of work what you have to show is one easy to follow diagram or a concise paragraph that can explain everything, that&amp;rsquo;s the sign you&amp;rsquo;re on the right track.  By making things simple you&amp;rsquo;re not proving what you&amp;rsquo;re working on wasn&amp;rsquo;t that complicated in the first place, but rather your skill and effort has been spent empowering anyone - including the busy c-suite executive - to be able to comprehend the issue properly.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
